[indistinct chatter]
[bell rings]
Ladies and gentlemen,
I invite you to proceed
to the Grand Hall.
[woman] You look fabulous.
You look very handsome.
I can't do it, Dottie. Could we
not pick it up another time?
-They could deliver to my house.
-John, it's an MBE, not a pizza.
You're being awarded
one of the highest honours
anyone can receive.
Excuse me, pal,
where's the exit?
-Directly down the hall.
-Right. That's me off.
-John.
-I'll embarrass myself, Dottie.
I'll say something I regret.
There's nothing you can say
she hasnae heard before.
She's a woman of the world.
She's a mum. She's a granny.
She's the queen
of the United Kingdom.
Davidson, you stop this right
now and listen to me, right?
You're here today
because you deserve to be.
You've earned this title
as much as anyone else
in this fancy palace.
It's starting.
Right, well, go save our seats.
-No. I can't do it, that's it.
-Davidson!
-[man] My lords, ladies...
-You get your arse in there now,
and you make us proud.
-[sighs]
-Go on.
[♪ "God Save the Queen"
playing]
[John] If I say something,
it's your fault.
[Dottie] All right,
it's always my fault.
[♪ "God Save the Queen"
continues playing]
[music stops]
-Fuck the Queen!
-[all gasp]
-You're all right.
-Sorry, everyone. Sorry, ma'am.
[♪ "Blue Monday" by New Order]
-Hi, Kenny.
-Morning, John. Late again.
[sighs] Traffic, you know.
Traffic was terrible.
Opal Fruits, one packet.
Opal Fruits, one packet,
duly noted.
Morning!
How you doing?
-Hiya, John.
-Hiya.
You'll do your back in,
you know.
-I'm all right.
-♪ How does it feel
♪ To treat me like you do?
♪ When you've laid
your hands upon me
♪ And told me who you are
♪ Thought I was mistaken
♪ I thought
I heard your words...
You polish your boots
for the big game, John?
Aye. Put dubbin on 'em
and everything.
John, I need to take you
shopping after football.
I'm on a short shift.
I can meet you at the bus stop
when the game's finished.
-Have I got to?
-Yes, you've got to.
You're starting big school
in two weeks.
I'm working at a house
near the park this morning.
-I might watch you play later.
-Oh, brilliant.
[chatter]
Come on, come on! Aye,
go at 'em! Come on, move.
Put a shift in. That's it.
-Jesus Christ!
-Ref! Ref!
-[blows whistle]
-Don't tackle him in the box!
Outside the box!
What are you doing?
-Oh! Absolute clown.
-All right, Billie?
Napier's gave away
another penalty.
It's all right, John'll save it.
[Billie groans] Murder.
[boy] Come on, John!
-[boy 2] Come on, Johnny.
-[boy 3] Come on, Johnny.
[blows whistle]
-[cheering]
-Yes! Yes, John!
Brilliant save, son, brilliant!
Good, good. Yes. That's it.
Pull it together, lads.
We've still got time.
Come on.
[John] Billie said it was
the best penalty save
he'd ever seen.
Said he's got a pal
at Berwick Rangers.
Tuck your shirt in, John.
I might even be able to get a
professional goalkeeping trial.
Fix your tie, John.
Dad saw it. He went loopy.
He started punching the air
and everything.
[sighs] Hurry up.
How does it feel?
[sighs] A bit weird. A bit...
-big, you know?
-You need room to grow.
Keep still a minute.
That'll do.
-Can I get changed?
-Yep.
Just need to find you
some shoes now, John.
-I might go fishing later.
-That's a nice thing to do.
Relax you a little.
How you feeling about
starting big school, John?
-Bit nervous.
-You'll be fine.
Just keep your head down,
stay out of trouble.
Work hard, John.
Course I will. I always do.
[man] Welcome to your first day
at Galashiels Secondary School.
Today marks an anniversary.
The start of a journey
that will define who you are.
It will determine
what you achieve
for the rest of your life.
And it's my responsibility
to make sure you leave here
having fully developed
your potential.
With regard to your manners
and your personal conduct,
I demand nothing
but the highest standards.
-Do you understand?
-Yes, sir.
-All right, Murray?
-All right, John?
-How you doing?
-Aye, good.
-I got extra chips.
-You jammy git.
Ladies.
How's your first day at school,
then?
All right.
-What's your name?
-Why would I tell you?
Why would you tell me? Well...
Cos you might want to come
to the pictures with me.
And how are you gonna pay
for that, then?
I've got a paper round.
I'm loaded.
Get lost.
He is. He's loaded.
Come on now, William.
Make an effort.
What did you have for lunch,
John?
Um... chips.
Just chips?
-Aye.
-That's chips twice in one day?
Chips twice in one day?
We need to keep an eye on that.
Don't want you getting spots.
-John. Sauce.
-Hmm. Sorry, Mum.
So, uh, I spoke to Billie today.
His pal from Berwick Rangers,
you know, the scout,
he's coming over
to watch you play in goal.
-Serious?
-Hm-hmm.
That penalty save
must've done the trick.
Magic.
[John] I dream of a Ledaean body
bent above a sinking fire, a...
a tale that she...
told of a harsh reproof
or trivial event...
that changed
some childish day to tragedy.
Uh, told, and it seemed...
-Told, and it seemed that...
-John, you all right?
It seemed that
our two natures blent into a...
In... into a...
-Into a...
-John, what's going on?
-Someone electrified his chair.
-Shh! John.
Permission to go to the toilet,
please, miss.
Aye. Away you go
and sort yourself out.
[water runs]
[school bell rings]
[boy] Come on!
-[John] Leave me alone.
-[boy 2] Do it. Do it.
-Piss off!
-Do the tic thing one time.
-Come on. Stop it, man.
-[boy] No, no, I've got it.
-[mimics John]
-[boy 2] I've got it as well.
-Look at John.
-[yells]
Piss off.
-No.
-Just get lost.
Look at him. [mimics John]
-How's school, Sharon?
-It's good, yeah.
Still got the same friends
and that in your class, or...?
I mean,
it's a wee bit different.
PE has changed the most.
But I've still got...
John.
-What are you doing?
-Um...
It's nothing.
Don't worry about it.
What's all this nonsense?
I don't know.
-Don't play the fool.
-I don't want to talk about it.
-John.
-I...
-John, where are you going?
-John.
-Don't let your dinner get cold.
-[door slams]
[footsteps on the stairs]
Right, everyone, come on.
Keep eating.
What's he playing at?
John, what's the matter
with you?
-Nothing.
-There's obviously something.
Acting the fool at the table.
Well... [sighs]
I've started doing this thing
with my neck and my eyes.
Jumping. Twitching.
Well, you're not doing it now.
You're just imagining it, John.
Have a hot bath
and an early night.
You'll be fine in the morning.
[John sighs]
-All right, Kerry?
-All right, John?
-This is my mum.
-You're keen aren't you, hmm?
Asking my daughter on a date
the first day of a new school.
-We're just watching a film.
-Hmm. Is it suitable?
-Is it suitable for your age?
-Aye, I think so.
Is there any swearing?
-Um... I don't think so.
-You don't think so?
So what's it about then,
this film?
It's about a man
who dresses as a woman. [laughs]
Well, that's not a good start,
is it?
-You won't be watching that.
-Mum. Jesus!
-Language, Kerry.
-[sighs]
Hey. I don't want
any funny business, OK?
[man] Ladies and gentlemen,
your projectionist tonight
is Eric,
who has a hot, thirsty job
which he does very well,
and, unlike you,
hasn't time to get himself
a refreshing drink of Kia Ora.
Thank you.
♪ Only the crumbliest
♪ Flakiest chocolate
♪ Tastes like chocolate
never tasted before
♪ Only the crumbliest
♪ Flakiest chocolate
♪ Tastes like chocolate
never tasted before
Suck my dick!
-[Kerry screams]
-I'm sorry. Kerry.
I'm sorry, Kerry.
I didn't realise what I did.
Get off me! Let go, you pervert!
-Sorry.
-I told you no funny business!
This is ridiculous.
-Out.
-Sorry.
Thank you.
[indistinct chatter]
Do you mind if I join you?
No, sit down, sit down.
So, am I right in assuming
you're all first-year students?
[students] Yes, sir.
-Settling in all right?
-Yes, sir.
How are you finding
the school dinners?
[spits] Fucking shite!
-Uh... Um...
-[room falls silent]
I'm... I'm sorry, sir.
I didn't mean to, sir.
Uh, I...
-What's your name, young man?
-Davidson, sir. Um...
John Davidson, sir.
Might I enquire as to which hand
you write with, Mr Davidson?
All I ask from you, Mr Davidson,
is a reassurance that
this never happen again.
Yes, sir. It won't, sir.
I'll spare you the embarrassment
of contacting your parents
in your first week.
But if I have cause
to summon you in here again...
-Yes, sir. Thank you, sir.
-Get out.
[boys chatter]
[loud chatter]
[whistles] John. Come here.
-What's going on with your neck?
-Nothing. Just stiff neck.
Just stiff neck?
What's wrong with your hand?
-Which one?
The one you're not using to
stop the ball hitting the net.
-Nothing, Billie.
-Nothing, Billie?
-Aye.
-Listen.
I've got a pal coming to watch.
Need you on your best game.
-Yeah?
-Aye, Billie. All good.
Right, come here. Come here.
See what you got here?
Use both hands, yeah?
Both hands.
I need you to use both of them.
-Yeah? Let's go, come on.
-No worries.
[Billie] Archie Gemmill-style.
Come on.
-Come on, John, focus.
-Both hands.
John, wake up, come on!
-What are you doing?
-Two of them.
-[whistle blows]
-Billie.
-Gerry, how you doing?
-Is this the lad?
-That's him. Johnny Davidson.
-Is he disabled?
-No.
He's just a bit nervous,
that's all.
Come on, John. Get eyes on him.
-Come on. Get in there.
-Go, go, go.
-[boys shout]
-[whistle blows]
You brought me all this way
for that?
[boys yell]
Gerry, he's usually great,
I don't know what's wrong.
Gerry, give the boy a chance.
John, wake up!
You're throwing this away, son.
He threw it away. Chance
of a lifetime, what did he do?
-David, stop it.
-Acted the clown.
Stop it.
That scout came all the way over
from Berwick Rangers.
-He'll hear you.
-I want him to hear me!
I was ashamed today!
I'm fed up with him,
and I'm fed up with you an' all.
[mother] So it's all my fault,
is it, that he didn't play well?
[David]
Why does he act like that?
[mother] Listen to you.
He's frightened of you,
probably,
the way you shout and act.
[girl] Can I put my name down
to bring the class rabbit
home from school?
It's too much responsibility,
cleaning out the cage.
-[John tics]
-[mother sighs]
-[John] Sorry.
-John, stop.
-John.
-Sorry.
Stop, please.
I don't mind picking up rabbit
poo. It's just like currants.
-Fucking rabbit shite!
-John!
Sorry. I'm sorry.
-You don't have to say that.
-I didn't mean to.
This is what I was telling you
earlier on, at the football.
What's this nonsense about?
-Oh!
-John! What the hell?
Take your plate, get away
from the table. I've had enough.
Swearing and spitting.
Oh, it's disgusting.
You've had enough?
I've had enough.
-Go on, then.
-Aye, I will.
Off to the pub, as usual.
Just when you're needed.
Over by the fireplace.
You eat there from now on.
Never use language like that in
this house again, you hear me?
And you never spit at me again.
Get down on the floor.
Get down on the floor, John!
-Mum, stop.
-[girl] You don't need to shout.
Face the fireplace.
If you want to spit,
you spit in the hearth.
Not at me, not at your father,
or your brother or sisters.
Sit down. You understand?
[tics]
[exhales]
[students] Fight, fight,
fight, fight, fight, fight!
[chanting continues]
-Fight, fight, fight, fight!
-[boys grunt]
[John] Get off me!
[groans]
-[chanting continues]
-[grunting]
Break it up, now!
-Head teacher's office.
-He swore at me!
-I can't help it!
-That's enough.
I can't help it.
-[grunts]
-[students groan]
Sorry, sir.
I cannae help it either.
He's a fucking freak.
He started it. He swore at me.
I expect better.
Do you understand?
-Yes, sir.
-Get out.
Davidson.
Sit down, Davidson.
My opinion, should it be
of interest to you...
I think you would be better
served at a different school.
-It wasn't my fault, sir.
-But it was.
It is, and it always will be,
as long as you continue
to behave like this.
I will give you the opportunity
here, now,
to admit that this is
all imagined, invented,
purely for attention.
It's not, sir.
Think very carefully,
Mr Davidson.
One last chance.
I can't help it.
Then there's nothing
we can do for you.
If it is not a scam,
you should be in an institution.
[tics]
What is the matter with you,
boy?
[John] I don't know, sir.
If you do not stop this
behaviour, prison waits.
And if not prison,
something far worse.
The real world, Mr Davidson,
outside of this school,
will not be as sympathetic
as we have been.
-Do you understand?
-Yes, sir.
I'll be in touch with
your parents shortly. Out!
-[sighs]
-[John] You cunt!
Mr Davidson.
[John sighs]
Before you leave...
[clears throat]
Now, before we have dinner,
I have something to tell you.
Your dad is leaving.
Leaving home, for good.
He's not coming back.
-Now eat your dinner.
-Why?
Because of me.
It's because of me,
Mum, isn't it?
It is what it is.
[John] Because of me,
though, isn't it?
Mum.
Answer me!
[tics]
Fuck off.
[exhales]
[tics]
[siren wails]
I've prescribed diazepam, five
milligrams, every three hours.
I don't understand,
he's only 13.
All he did
was fall in the river.
I'm not convinced he fell,
Mrs Davidson.
-[John] I'm going mad.
-[mother] No. Don't be silly.
-I made Dad leave.
-No, John. No.
Just...
I can't take it.
I just feel like killing myself.
No, don't say things like that.
Everything's going to be fine.
We're going to get you better
in next to no time.
It's OK, John.
Shh.
It's all OK.
Yes. Shh. Go to sleep now.
Go to sleep, John.
Go to sleep.
[birds sing]
[tics]
[sighs]
They're wondering
what you were shouting at.
-[tics]
-[sighs]
Shh, John. Come on.
-Sixty-watt bulb will be fine.
-[tics]
Now, um, need to get
some potatoes for dinner.
-[John] What are they for?
-For boiling.
-Two of those, they'll be fine.
-I'll get four just in case.
-What else?
-Fuck.
What else do I need, John?
I need some new toothpaste,
Mum.
Have you finished
your current one?
-Almost.
-Wait till it's all gone.
before we get a new one.
-No worries.
-Remind me to get Oxo cubes.
Is that for a stew? A stew!
-Stop it.
-Sorry.
[Murray] Johnny D. Jesus!
-How you doing, pal?
-I thought I heard you.
-You good?
-Yeah.
Hiya, Mrs Davidson. I'm Murray,
John's pal from school.
Murray, how are you? I didn't
recognise you. All grown up.
-You're looking well.
-Thank you.
I've been over in Australia.
I had a job and everything,
but my mum's not doing too well,
so I had to come home.
I'm sorry about that, Murray.
It's all right.
Fancy a wee drink, John?
Have a wee catch-up?
No, he can't drink, Murray.
He's on medication.
-All right.
-Hm-hmm.
-Could maybe just go for a walk?
-A wank. That would be good.
Would you like that, John?
A walk with Murray?
To give me a break?
And I'll see you at home?
Hmm.
-It's good to see you.
-See you at the front?
-Yeah.
-Bye.
-[tics]
-Now, I need to get some coffee.
It's difficult to explain.
It's sort of like...
an impulse in my brain
that makes me do things,
or say things that I shouldn't.
It's called Tourette's syndrome,
apparently.
Well, that's good then,
that they know what it is.
Aye. It was brilliant
for the first few days
until they said
there was no cure.
Jesus, John, I'm sorry.
So what happens now then?
-Looking for a job?
-[John] Aye, I'd love one,
but, you know, what can I do?
What will they let me do?
Anyway, tell us about Australia.
-Oh, it was mental.
-Was it?
Travelled all about.
Saw the Great Barrier Reef,
worked on a sheep farm.
-Wow.
-I had to come back early cos...
I don't know if you ever
met my mum, did you?
She's got cancer.
-Cancer of the liver.
-Oh, Jesus, Murray.
Given her six months to live.
[John] Sorry, pal.
[Murray] Want to come in
for something to eat?
-[John] No, I'm good, thank you.
-Come on.
[John]
I need to get back. I'm tired.
-Gotta take my tablets. Hitler!
-OK. No worries.
[Murray] You wanna
do something soon,
-give me a shout.
-No worries.
-See you soon, Murray.
-See you.
Smells like spaghetti bolognese.
Sure you don't want some?
No, I'm OK. Hitler!
[woman] Oi.
What's wrong with
my spaghetti bolognese?
I'm sure it's great.
I just need to be getting home.
[woman] What's your name?
John.
John, get your arse in here.
Be on the table in two minutes.
-No, honestly...
-[slams]
[sighs] Fuck you in particular.
Fuck, fuck you in particular.
[sighs] God, John.
[tics]
Come on, John.
Oh.
Come on in, love. I'm Dottie.
You're gonna die of cancer.
Ha-ha!
For fuck's sakes, John.
I'm sorry.
Right.
Well, it's nice to meet you too.
I'm really, really sorry.
You're all right.
You know, that's the most honest
anyone's been with me in months.
Well, come on. Go and sit down.
Are you sure?
You're all right, I don't bite.
[chuckles]
-Shall I take my shoes off?
-No, we're not fancy in here.
John? It's getting cold.
Aye, you carry on. No worries.
[exhales]
Right. Let's eat.
[tics] Cunt.
[tics]
[loud crashing]
What the hell was that?
Murray?
I don't know.
Mum, he's not been well.
He's on medication.
I thought as much.
[dad] Do you wanna check
if he's all right?
[sighs] Can I not eat first?
Right, well, let's just
give him a minute, OK?
[knocks on door]
[Dottie] John?
[sighs softly]
[sighs]
John...
Just breathe. [sighs]
-Fuck off.
-John.
Hello.
-Are you OK?
-Aye, I'm fine, thank you.
I just wanted to say that, um...
-when I was in the bathroom...
-Yeah, I know. I saw.
Right, well, um...
I just wanted
to apologise for that.
You're all right.
What medication are you on?
I'm not.
I've been a mental health nurse
now for years.
So...
-It's called haloperidol.
-Ooh.
I'm a lot worse
if I don't take it.
I missed one today and that's
probably why that happened.
Have you ever thought
about stopping it long term?
Not really.
I don't think you are OK.
How are things at home?
Come on. I'll heat up your food.
[sniffles]
Fucking pussy.
[sighs]
Mind your head.
[spitting]
[spits] Fuck's sakes, John.
[spits]
[whistles]
♪ Mild green...
[clears throat]
That was good food.
Thanks, John.
Dottie's dying of cancer!
Sorry, Dottie.
Oh, fuck!
Oh, fuck off, you cunt!
-Sorry, everyone.
-Right, John.
If you're gonna visit us more
often, which I hope you are,
I need to speak to you
about your language.
Aye, OK.
We have one rule in this house.
And that's if you do anything
you can't help,
you never, ever
have to apologise for it.
If you're out in the street with
people who don't understand you,
then fine, you know, apologise,
whatever, but in this house...
where we know you can't help it,
you know, where we know
you don't mean it...
well, it all means diddly squat.
It's the apologising
that drives me mad.
You don't need to apologise.
OK?
OK. [clears throat]
Aye, OK.
-Thank you.
-Great. Thank you.
[tics]
[Dottie] John, leave that.
We're starting.
Aye, just one second.
I've told John
that he can stay here.
Tonight?
Aye, tonight, or for good,
if he wants.
-Mum.
-What?
Have you lost your mind?
With everything
you've got going on?
The way I see it is like this,
I've got six months to live.
I can sit here
feeling sorry for myself,
watching Neighbours
and eating Pringles,
or I can help this lad.
-Where's he gonna sleep?
-The box room,
if he doesn't mind pink.
John, do you know blackjack?
-Is that pontoon?
-It is.
Aye, I can play that.
I've got two aces.
I'm sorry, everyone.
No apologies.
Right.
We'll just pretend we didn't
hear that, shall we, Murray?
Yeah.
Chris?
Great, we're all agreed.
Hit me.
Hit me again.
[they laugh]
[music playing on TV]
[man] As we said in practice,
very fast...
-How was Murray, John, hmm?
-Hmm.
Lots of stories from
his adventure, I expect.
John?
Lots of stories
from his adventure, hm?
-I'm moving out.
-What did you say?
[clears throat] I'm moving out.
I'm going to live
at Murray's house.
If I didn't know any better,
I'd assume
that was one
of your nonsensical tics.
His mum, Dottie, said I should
discuss it with you first but...
that's what I'm going to do.
Hmm. I thought Murray said
his mum was sick.
[John] She is. She's got cancer.
Oh.
I think you're being naive,
John.
They're looking for someone
to look after her.
Is that what this is all about?
Is this her idea, is it?
No, it's what I want.
But you're needed here, John.
Your brother and sisters
are gone, your dad's left,
and I'm not getting
any younger.
[she sighs]
I'm stopping the drugs as well.
Well, I've heard it all now.
Was that Murray's mum's idea?
-She understands, she's a nurse.
-Oh, is she?
And what's this, hmm?
I'm a nurse, John.
Fifteen years.
And I'm also your mother.
Without your tablets,
you punch, you swear,
and spit and upset people.
You forgotten that, John?
I still do all that now, Mum.
You do it less when
you're on the tablets, John!
[she sighs]
[exhales]
Murray's mum has no idea
how hard it is to cope with you.
I need a break.
You need a break.
-I'm sorry.
-John.
[♪ "The Changingman"
by Paul Weller]
I like black, what can I say?
Well, then this is brilliant.
I'm not gonna have to do
any more washing-up
now you've moved in.
Aye, you can fuck off, Murray.
And that wasn't a tic.
So you've never been out
in Gala then?
-No.
-You never been to the Bizz?
-Are you fucking deaf?
-The Golden Lion? The Harrows?
[scoffs]
You've never lived, mate.
I went to the Golden Lion once,
with my dad, for a pint,
-but that was years ago.
-Well, that doesn't count.
The day you're off those pills,
me and you, out on the randan.
Man, can't wait.
Was that a tic?
Course it was.
-That was just me being stupid.
-[laughs]
-I'm coming for you!
-Don't! Don't! Don't!
No, don't!
[laughs]
-Look at the state of me!
-Aye, you look great.
-[tics]
-Oh, God!
-Sorry, Dottie.
-[laughs] It's all right.
-Really ticky.
-I'm not surprised.
You're almost weaned off
the tablets.
-How do you feel in yourself?
-I feel better. Sleeping better.
-Less headaches and that.
-Good.
That's what we want to hear.
Right, get me some grapes.
-Grapes.
-Oh, God.
-Do you want red or green?
-Uh, green, please.
John, is there lentils in that,
or is there not?
Um...
No, you're fine with that one,
Dot.
Great. Two more of those.
[woman over speaker]
Clean-up on aisle five, please.
All right, Suzy?
How you doing today?
-Good, John. How are you?
-Good. I find you attractive.
-How are you, Dottie?
-I'm good, love. How are you?
-Good. You keeping well?
-I don't care.
-How's your mum?
-[John] She's a cunt.
-Give her my love, won't you?
-Fuck off.
Show me your knockers.
[softly] Fuck off.
Right, John.
Oh, right, now, chicken stock.
Chicken's cock.
-Crap.
-[groans]
-Sorry, Dottie.
-It's all right. [laughs]
You can't stand on my right,
you know that.
-All right.
-I did tell you that.
It's my fault now, is it?
You've given me a thick lip,
you numpty.
-Sorry, Dot.
-[groans]
[Dottie] But you can't be
on medication all your life,
you know,
bottling everything up.
-What sort of life is that?
-I fucked that up, as usual.
No, you didn't.
-How's your lip?
-It's fine.
It's my fault for standing
on the wrong side of you.
[chuckles]
Mum!
[sighs] John.
How are you?
Dottie, this is my mum.
It's nice to meet you,
Mrs Davidson.
-I'm Murray's mum.
-Pussy.
-Sorry, Mum.
-How are you, John?
It's been a while
since you came to visit.
I know. Um, maybe I'll pop over
this weekend. [tics]
Um, John.
Why don't you go to the post
office and get me some stamps?
-[John tics]
-That should be enough.
[John] I'll see you soon, Mum.
See you next weekend.
Bye, John.
I can see
he's off the medication.
He stopped it gradually.
He feels better for it.
[John tics]
He's settled in well.
We love having him around.
John says you're a nurse.
That's right, yeah.
Patience of a saint.
Whatever patience I had,
it was used up years ago.
Aye, well,
I was at Dingleton Hospital
five years, mental health nurse.
-So you know there's no cure?
-Aye.
Hm-hmm. And you've
not been well yourself.
[Dottie] Oh, I'm fine.
The punching,
spitting, swearing.
It's a lot to take on
in your condition.
We're helping each other.
[sighs] Well, I'd be grateful
if you would ask John
to visit home more often.
-[Dottie] Aye. I will.
-Hmm.
[♪ "Born of Frustration"
by James plays loudly]
What's this? Top of the Pops?
I'm off the medication. Murray's
going to take me out clubbing.
So you're perfecting
your dance moves?
-Aye. What do you think?
-Great. [chuckles]
I'll leave you to it.
♪ Where's the confusion?
Wait.
-What are you doing?
-Smartening myself up.
No, take it out now.
These jeans feel weird, Murray,
round the crotch.
When we get in there, John,
can you just relax
and don't do anything weird?
-I won't.
-Yeah?
-Yeah.
-Good man.
All right.
-Shall I put this in here?
-Put it away, John.
Right, this is us now.
Come on. Thank you.
[coins rattle]
-There you go.
-[man] Thank you.
[whistles]
-[Murray] What do you think?
-I love it, man.
I can feel that bass
in my chest.
Yeah. Wait, I'll go and get us
a drink. You get us a seat.
No worries.
[♪ "Alright" by Supergrass]
Two pints of Tennent's, please.
What's your name?
-What?
-What's your name?
-Marie.
-Can I buy you a drink?
-What?
Sure.
Pernod and black, please,
and my pals will take the same.
John.
You don't hang about.
-Are you impressed?
-Aye.
Right, they want
three Pernod and black.
OK, I'll get them, will I?
Three Pernod and black, please.
Getting 'em now.
[indistinct chatter]
-I'm so sorry, pal. Sorry.
-[grunts]
-You fucking prick!
-[Murray] Oi!
Get your fucking hands off him!
John!
Fuck off!
-Out of here!
-Fucking wanker!
Fuck off.
-[Murray] It wasn't him!
-[John] Fucking wanker!
John, are you OK, man?
[tics]
Give us a kiss, you wanker.
You can't take him,
it's not his fault.
I raped a girl in there.
I didn't. I didn't rape anyone.
Hey, fuck off!
Hey, where are you gonna
take him, man?
John, it's OK. John.
-Back, back!
-All right.
John, phone us when you
get there. My mum will sort it.
-[tics]
-John, when you get there,
phone my mum, please.
John? Phone Mum.
-Fuck.
-[siren wails]
[John] You're a fucking pig!
I've seen your fucking
bald spot! [tics]
Fuck off! Wanker!
[policeman]
You got some death wish, Johnny?
[banging]
[groans]
[door opens]
What's wrong with your back?
[John] It's just a tic.
I know you better than that.
Let's see.
Oh, your face has gone down.
[gasps]
Is that all from the club?
Aye.
I will give Murray an earful
when he wakes up,
letting you get in a state
like that.
Don't do that, Dottie.
Don't give him a hard time.
[sighs]
It was the best night
of my life. I loved it.
There you go.
Thanks.
I danced with this girl.
Her name was Marie.
Well, I hope she was worth it,
because the other lad's dad's
a solicitor.
They're taking it to court.
They said we'll know
in a couple of months.
[sighs]
[Dottie] Oh, John, we can't keep
letting you get into trouble
like this.
-I'm not going back on tablets.
-And I'm not saying you should.
But you need a focus,
you know...
You're better
when you're keeping busy.
You need a job.
[chuckles quietly] Dottie.
-[Dottie] Do you want a job?
-Aye, I'd love one.
Great.
Tommy at the community centre
is looking for an assistant.
They're interviewing next week.
I'm putting your name down.
-I won't get it.
-Well, somebody has to.
Not someone like me.
[John] Listen,
I'm going to fuck this up.
I know I'm going
to fuck this up.
You're not. Right,
we've waited long enough, John.
You're gonna have to go in.
[tuts]
Look, you want this job, right?
-[John] Yeah.
-You're gonna be great.
-[John] I'm nervous.
-I know, love. I know. Let's...
[sighs] Well, let's do
some breathing. All right?
I want you to close your eyes
and breathe it all out.
-Go on. [exhales]
-[exhales]
There we go. Now, I want you
to imagine yourself on a beach.
Right, secluded beach.
And all you can hear
is the sound of the waves
lapping on the shore.
And the sand, it's soft,
and it's white and it's warm.
My feet are burning.
[clears throat]
Right.
-How are you doing, Irene?
-Yeah, all right, thanks.
-Is, um, Tommy already in?
-He's in the hall.
Right, well, he's a bit nervous,
so he might be more extreme.
-Hello!
-But you'll get used to it.
-Understood.
-How are you? How you doing?
-Nice to meet you.
-Nice to meet you, too.
-Oh!
-[clattering]
I'm really, really sorry
about that.
No worries, John.
[tics softly]
[man whistles]
This is Tommy, our caretaker.
-Oh!
-Oop, sorry.
I'll help you with that.
-Ooh, the boy's keen.
-[Irene] Tommy, this is John.
He's come to chat
about the vacant position.
-All right, John?
-Nice to meet you.
-How are you?
-Good.
-Dottie told me a lot about you.
-We'll leave you two together.
-[tics]
Aye. Irene, did you get
that note about the blue roll?
-Yeah. No worries.
-Right. Thank you.
-All right, John?
-All right.
Right, OK, be on your desk.
-All right, John?
-Yeah, good.
-John.
-Nice to meet you.
You, too. Uh, right, I'll give
you a rundown of the place.
Give me your cock in my hand.
Fuck's sakes.
-So, this is the main hall.
-Right.
And, uh, to be honest, a lot of
what I do is health and safety.
You know, fire escapes, fire
extinguishers, smoke alarms.
-Aye, easy peasy.
-That kind of stuff, you know.
Uh, if you were to get the job,
and it's an "if", remember,
because I'm seeing
a few youngsters.
-I know.
-OK. Just so you know that.
Wrinkly bastard.
You've got different events,
uh, require different things.
So, like, a wee council meeting
could be
just a couple of tables.
Then again, you could be laying
out 200 seats for a pantomime.
-Or a school theatre production.
-I'm a paedophile.
Sorry, it was a tic.
That's all right, it's OK.
-Want me to show you outside?
-Aye, that would be good.
Right, good, good.
[John tics]
-Um, uh...
-[banging]
I need to fix this.
There we go.
Right, so, we plant these
every spring,
so they need watering
and weeding,
and fed. You know about plants?
Aye. I love plants.
Two in my garden.
Right, good. Um, this area
is the bane of my life.
Do you ever shut the fuck up?
Bane of my life, this area,
because of this.
This provides cover
for the smokers.
So the smokers come out here
and they smoke.
And then what do they do?
They drop their filthy fags.
Filthy fags! Filthy fags!
Filthy fags! I'm gay.
No, I'm not. Yes, I am.
Filthy fags!
It's quite echoey in there,
isn't it?
Aye, it is quite... echoey.
Just close the door behind you.
You OK with dogs?
-Aye, I love dogs.
-This is Rosie.
-Hello, Rosie. How are you?
-Um...
-You OK sitting there?
-[bangs]
-You all right?
-Yeah, I'm good.
-OK. Don't hit the furniture.
-Sorry, sorry.
All right, OK, just take a seat.
Right.
So, now we get to
the most important part
-of the interview, John.
-Bum sex.
And that is, can you make
a decent cup of tea?
[John] Oh, aye. I'm good at tea.
I like it strong, lots of milk,
three sugar.
No bother, Tommy.
[kettle boils]
And remember, put the water
in first, then the milk.
OK, yeah. I do that as well.
Right, we'll get to you
in a minute, John.
So, what have they told you
about me?
Um, they just said that you've
not been very well lately.
Right. The plan is to get in
a youngster, you learn the job,
so that if I've got a hospital
appointment, or whatever...
-Aye.
-..they can step in
-and keep things going.
-Hmm, yeah.
Well, I read a bit about
the job, you know,
and the hours and that.
-Interested in giving it a go.
-Right.
-You reliable?
-Aye.
I'm always early, always.
I have to be, you know.
Cos I need someone to be here
on time, to open up,
and to be here to lock up
when I'm not here.
-Aye, any time. Any time.
-Right.
-Good with your hands?
-I was good at school, you know.
Woodwork and metalwork and that.
But I'm keen to learn, and...
I don't mind getting
my hands dirty, you know?
-OK.
-I'm a lazy bastard.
-So, you don't mind hard work?
-No.
In fact, when I'm concentrating
on the job or a project,
I think it really helps me.
Right.
-That's hot.
-Aye.
There you go, Tommy. [spits]
I'm really sorry.
I'll take that one.
Aye, that's a good idea.
Hm-hmm.
I've seen quite a few youngsters
for this job.
-Aye.
-And I don't think
I'm breaking confidentiality
when I tell you
that that is
the best cup of tea yet.
[John] Great.
[Tommy sighs] So...
I use spunk for milk.
Right, so,
have you any questions for me?
Um...
Oh, aye, yeah. Um...
I might have to take a few days
off work, in a few months,
because I've got a court trial
coming up.
-Just that.
-So you've not even got the job
but already you're looking
for a day off?
No, no. I'm just saying that...
You're fucking it up, John.
Um, I'm just saying that,
if I were to get the job,
I'd have to take that time.
I just wanted to be honest.
Right.
-Get in a wee scrape, did you?
-Aye.
I've had a bit of bad luck
recently.
-Was it your fault?
-No.
OK. That's good enough for me.
-Any other questions?
-Um...
I can do the job, you know.
-I can do it.
-Hm-hmm.
But just the obvious question,
really, um...
Are you OK with the tics
and the swearing?
What tics? What swearing?
[chuckles]
[dog yelps, whines]
Uh...
Just a wee word of warning,
John. Uh...
You ever do that
to my dog again,
and I'll tear your fucking
heart out. Understand?
Right, well...
Thanks for seeing me.
OK, I'll get off, then.
-All right, Rosie?
-[dog pants]
[indistinct chatter]
-Oh, hiya, John.
-All right, pal. How you doing?
Good, good.
-Paper and Opal Fruits, please.
-So, how you been keeping?
Ah, not so bad. Had a
job interview today, Kenny.
-Oh, right. How did that go?
-I hit the boss's dog.
Ach, well, never mind.
You can always come back
to your old paper round.
I might hold you to that, Kenny.
I'll see you later.
Take care. Yes, love?
Slut!
What did you say?
I'm sorry, miss.
I've got Tourette's.
-What did you just say to me?
-I'm really sorry.
I mean no harm.
I can't help what I say.
-I'm sorry.
-Fuck off!
[exhales]
[kettle boils]
Anyone home?
[clears throat] Dot?
-What are you doing?
-[stifled laughter]
Wait a minute, John.
[screams] You got it!
[Chris] Tommy called.
You got the job.
The job?
-You start on Monday.
-Oh, my God!
Well done, John.
-Are you serious?
-[Dottie] Aye.
-You deserve it.
-Well done, Davidson.
I can't believe that.
It went so bad.
-You deserve that.
-[laughs]
-And now you've...
-God, I've got a job.
I don't wanna steal
your thunder...
-Aye, but you will.
-Um...
Chris and I went
to the hospital today.
You're dying of cancer,
you old fucker. [tics]
I'm not, John. Um...
They made a mistake.
-It's not cancer.
-[chuckles]
-It's called haema...
Haemanagi... ngioma.
-Ham shandy, you cunt.
-[laughter]
What is it, love?
Haemangioma.
You know, it's a lump.
But anyway, it's not cancer.
It looks like cancer,
but it's not. [laughs]
Come here.
[Murray] I love you, Mum.
I love you all!
[laughs and kisses]
-[John] I can't believe that.
-All right, John, here. Um...
Go to the Chinese and get
what anyone wants.
A banquet. It's my treat,
double celebration.
-[music playing]
-[food sizzles]
-Thank you. See you later.
-[woman] See you, bye.
-[metal scraping]
-Come here.
[groans]
[man] Fucking do him.
Fucking do him!
[groaning]
-Fucking do him!
-I am! Fucker!
-Who's this?
-That fucking...
Move, move, move!
Move, move!
-[groans]
-[muffled voices]
Who you calling
a fucking slut now, eh?
Fuck you!
Fucking go, get out of here!
Think you're a fucking
tough guy, eh?
Take the fucking warning.
[muffled groan]
You've been fucking warned.
-[grunts]
-[Dottie] John, it's all right.
It's all right.
-Dottie's here. I'm here.
-[grunts]
[Dottie shushes softly]
Hmm.
Sweetheart.
I'm gonna have to call your mum.
-No.
-John.
-John, I have to.
You'll just worry her.
It's fine.
[sighs]
That job starts on Monday.
[Dottie] Tommy says you're
to take as long as you need, hm?
Job's yours.
-It's not going anywhere.
-[John] That's good.
Oh, love, love. You're all
right, you're all right.
Come on, sweetheart, calm down.
-[grunts]
-You're all right. Shh.
-I know.
-[grunts]
[shushes]
I know.
-It's all right.
-[exhales]
You're all right, hey?
[tics]
-[groans]
-Come on. Shh. Come on.
Come on.
I know. Hmm?
I'm tired of this, Dottie.
I'm so tired.
[Dottie] I know you are, love.
I know.
[♪ "Merry Xmas Everybody"
by Slade]
[tics]
[song continues in the distance]
How you getting on
with those chairs, son?
[John] Aye, no bother, Tommy.
[Tommy] Oh, my God.
You've got them straighter
than I could ever have got them.
Gotta be straight, Tom.
I gotta count them as well.
Gotta be ten chairs, four rows.
An even number,
otherwise it's not right.
Is it the numbers that gets
to you, or is it the shape?
Ah, it's all of it.
If it's not right,
then I just think bad things
are going to happen.
[Tommy] Like what?
Well, sometimes I'm putting
my hand under boiling water,
and I've gotta do it four times,
otherwise you're going to die.
-Excuse me?
-I know. [chuckles]
But, like, another thing I do,
and this is really weird,
is I'm walking down the street
and I see a lamppost,
and say it's not straight
or it's at the wrong angle,
or a different colour or
something, I have to kiss it.
-You have to kiss a lamppost?
-Yeah.
[Tommy] Ah, you never
told me that at your interview.
-You never asked.
-Yeah.
[Tommy] And it's always the tics
that cause the problem?
Aye, yeah, always the tics.
You know what I was thinking?
Tell you what I was thinking.
How would you feel about
letting people into your head
the way you let me
into your head?
-Nah, I can't do that.
-No, hear me out.
Cos I don't think
Tourette's is the problem.
I think the problem is we don't
know enough about Tourette's.
So, if you don't educate
the police
and the doctors
and the teachers,
if you don't educate them,
-nothing's gonna change.
-So what do you want me to do?
Walk into a police station
calling them "pigs",
or into a school and say,
"I'm a paedo"?
Yes, abso-fucking-lutely.
There, you see?
You see? You're not
the only one that can swear.
I swear when I feel strongly
about something,
when I feel passionate
and I feel strongly about this.
Why don't you stop
giving a flying fuck
about what people think
about you and educate them?
Ya cunt, you.
See what I did there?
That's emphasis.
-I saw that.
-Ya cunt, you.
-Go on.
I put a bit of leg movement
in there.
-Yeah, you got a carabiner.
-Fucking cunt, you.
[John] I need that time off,
Tom, for the day in court.
I know, I saw that.
You OK about it?
Terrified.
Fucking hell, John.
-Sorry.
-John.
-It's Christmas.
-[laughs]
Seriously.
Jesus Christ almighty.
-Right, OK.
-[laughs]
What's next?
What's next is
keeping my balls protected.
[lawyer] My client
is now going to give evidence.
Mr Davidson,
will you please make your way
-to the witness box?
-[clears throat]
Mr Davidson,
will you take the oath?
I will.
[judge] Please raise your right
hand, and repeat after me...
I swear by Almighty God...
-..that I will tell the truth...
-..the whole truth...
-No, I won't!
Please, can someone explain
the reason for this contempt?
My lord, if I may,
Mr Davidson, on occasion,
shouts things uncontrollably.
Impulsive comments. He neither
means them or can control them.
Sexist, homophobic,
misogynistic...
Don't forget racist, you wanker.
[lawyer] And racist.
Based on personal experience,
I can assure you
he is well versed in all manner
of racist comments,
many of which not even
I have encountered,
but all completely
out of his control.
We lodged production number 71
detailing a condition
known as Tourette's syndrome.
Yes, I have read the document,
but I have also considered
production number 107
-from Mr Barrowman...
-Fuck, cunt.
..which claims that
Tourette's syndrome
is not a recognised condition.
That it cannot be diagnosed,
and therefore
is irrelevant to this case.
[Barrowman] Thank you, my lord.
Mr Davidson, the oath,
one more time, if you please,
exactly as it is
pronounced by me.
OK.
Please raise your right hand,
and repeat...
I swear by Almighty God...
..that I will tell the truth...
..that I will tell the tru...
You're a cunt!
[hushed chatter]
Mr Davidson,
please leave the court.
-That I will tell the truth.
-Mr Davidson,
please leave my court.
Mr Davidson, if you do not
remove yourself from my court,
I will have you man-handled.
Mr Davidson,
-please leave my court.
-I swear by Almighty God...
I swear by Almighty God
that I will tell the truth.
-Mr Davidson!
-Cunt!
-Cunt, fuck, cunt!
-Leave!
John. Come on, love.
It's all right.
[tics]
[tics] I'm a retard. I'm a spaz.
You fucked it up.
You fucked it up, John. [tics]
[tics]
-Tommy.
-[continues to tic]
It's not going well, Tommy.
He called the judge a cunt.
-Well, that's not good.
-No.
[Tommy] John is, without doubt,
the best employee
I've ever had.
Does... Does he shout? Yes.
Does he swear? Yes.
Does he mean any harm?
Absolutely not.
-[tics]
-His tics are uncontrollable.
There's times, two or three
times a day, his right hand
will just thrust right out
like that, clenched fist.
It'll come to about an eighth
of an inch away from my face.
That's how good he is. He's got
it down to an absolute fine art.
Two or three times a day, he'll
skelp me in my homos, right?
Now... Can I say homos?
I'm sure it's not any worse
than what we've heard already.
All right, so I can say it?
You know what I mean
when I say homos? Balls?
Meat and two veg? Crown jewels?
Gonads? Testicles?
-Bollocks!
-[judge] Thank you, Mr Trotter.
-I think we have it.
-Right, I just wanted to check.
OK. It is a medical condition.
Right?
It exists. I see it every day.
Now, I understand
that some people
are saying that he's pretending.
Can I ask, why would you pretend
to have a condition
that results in you being
hit with a crowbar?
That resulted
in you being humiliated
and ridiculed at school
by being refused
to sit your higher exams
that could improve your life?
That stops you
having a relationship?
Who, who would pretend
to have such a condition?
[tics] Me.
Now, I know
John's a proud young man,
and he wouldn't like me
using the word "disability",
but can I just ask,
if a blind man walks into a bar,
and crashes into another guy,
would it end up in court?
Huh?
Now, that young man over there
would not harm a fly.
He is, he is the nicest,
kindest, most respectful
young man I have ever met.
And he makes
a damn fine cup of tea.
Spunk for milk.
Can I...
Sorry. Sorry, Your Honour.
Thank you, Mr Trotter.
[man] John, did that outcome
surprise you?
No. The sheriff said it should
never have gone to court.
[man 2] Dottie, what was the
most significant moment for you?
Oh, well, it's when he said
that the police needed
to learn from this experience.
Uh, Tommy Trotter,
friend of the family.
Just wanted to say what that boy
did in there was incredible.
-You can quote me on that.
-[man] Are you proud of John?
Me?
Well, I'm always proud of John.
[man 2] So, John,
where do you go from here?
[Tommy]
I'll tell you where he goes.
Back to
the community centre with me,
and he helps me clean out
those drains.
-That's what he does.
-[chuckles]
[tics]
[whistles]
Home time!
Right, that's me.
I'm off to see Tommy today,
Irene.
Had a hospital appointment.
Will you tell him
bingo's cancelled on Thursday?
I will indeed.
See you later, Irene.
[Irene] See you, John.
[whistles]
[knocks at door]
[John] Tommy?
Tommy!
[dog whines]
Tommy?
-Hello, Rosie.
-[dog whines]
Are you OK, girl?
-Tommy?
-[thuds]
Oh, God.
[siren wails]
Police.
Hello? Anyone here?
Hit the lights, will you?
All right, son?
What's happened?
Um...
I came in and, um...
I brought him some beers.
I killed him.
Fuck's sakes.
-I killed him.
-Killed who, son?
He's in there.
OK.
I need you to stay exactly
where you are, OK?
Yeah. No worries.
[door opens]
I killed him.
-[priest] And now for a hymn...
-[sighs]
from Scottish Anglican cleric
Henry Francis Lyte,
"Abide With Me".
[all] ♪ Abide with me
♪ Fast falls the eventide
-♪ The darkness deepens
-[John tics]
♪ Lord, with me abide
[tics]
-♪ When other helpers fail
-Fuck off, John!
-[tics]
-♪ And comforts flee
♪ Help of the helpless
-[tics]
-♪ O abide with me
Fuck off, John! Ha-ha.
John?
-Oi, Davidson!
-What?
I'm taking you for lunch.
-Come on, lunch.
Can't hear you.
[John] Where'd you get these
tomatoes from? [clears throat]
[Dottie] The market. Why?
[John] Bit mushy.
[Dottie] Aye, you're not wrong.
Could you imagine yourself
living here, John?
-What, here?
-Aye.
In a flat?
Aye.
You know what?
We love you to bits, but...
you've been in that box room
five years and I...
Well, I think it's starting
to stunt your growth.
You need your independence.
There's a council flat
come up in that block.
[sighs] And I've got us
an appointment in ten minutes,
if you're interested.
There's no pressure.
Aye, I could live here.
Why not?
Great.
If the application
was successful,
the council would
measure the damp.
-Oh, John...
-Whatever needs doing, really.
-[Dottie] Look at that.
-There's no fireplace, Dottie.
Aye, well, there won't be
in a flat, love.
I could use a bucket, though.
And, of course,
there's a little balcony.
[John] Oh, wow, look at that.
Amazing.
I'm gonna jump.
The council can add
security bars. We do that a lot.
Aye, that would be a good idea.
So what do you think, John?
It's a shithole!
Aye. I like it.
Yeah?
OK, here we go.
Thank you.
-Excited to show you it.
-Yeah?
[exhales]
Right, that's the last box.
-Sure you're all right, John?
-No worries.
I'll go get in the lift, Mum.
See you soon, man.
-Thanks, pal.
-OK. So, um...
-you'll be all right then?
-Aye.
Aye, I'll be fine, Dot. Come on.
[Dottie] It's gonna be quiet
at home without you.
[John] I know. [chuckles]
And, um, well, you'll come
for Sunday lunch, won't you?
-Of course I will.
-Great.
Oh, and, uh, remember,
-no swearing.
-[chuckles]
See you later, Dot.
[door closes]
I'll go for a wank.
[tuts] Fuck off, John.
[tics]
Fuck off!
-[man] Who's he shouting at?
-[man 2] No one.
Cunt!
-[John tics]
-You all right, mate?
-Aye, no worries.
-Who you swearing at, then?
No one, it's just what I do.
It's a medical condition.
-What?
-Where do you live?
-Fuck off, nosy.
-[laughter]
That was a tic.
You just gotta ignore 'em.
-You'll get used to me.
-[laughter]
Anyway,
I better be getting back.
Got a frozen lasagne
defrosting in here.
Which flat's yours then?
[♪ "Numb" by Portishead]
[laughter and chatter]
[man] Oh, are youse all right?
How's the bar?
Fucking tell her.
Let's fucking tell her.
[chatter continues]
-You all right, mate?
-Aye.
Brought you a beer.
Thanks.
[scoffs]
What's with the bars?
Stop me...
jumping over the side.
Jeez.
It's a nice flat.
Could do with spending
some money on it, though.
What do you mean?
Well, get like
a big fuck-off TV.
A new sofa.
I can't afford that, pal.
-Come work for me.
-I've got a job.
In your spare time,
come work for me.
-But then again...
-What?
Maybe, I don't know...
-Well...
Your disability might
get in the way.
It's not a fucking disability.
I can do whatever you need
doing. What do you need?
Take that.
[John tics]
You all right?
-It's in the bag.
-What?
-It's in the fucking bag.
-Oh, right. [clears throat]
I've got a bag like this,
you know. I use it for work.
Really good pockets.
Is this what I think it is?
Is this for Danny?
Look at that.
Half-price heroin! Fuck off!
[tics]
I'm selling drugs! [tics]
Pigs! Pigs!
Pigs!
-[whistles]
-[policeman] All right, mate?
-Come here a minute.
-All right, lads?
-How are you doing, officers?
-Stop where you are. Come here!
Come here.
You been taking
illegal substances?
No, no, it's nothing like that.
I've got, um...
I've got drugs up my jumper.
I've got Tourette's syndrome.
-I can't help what I say.
-Is that right, aye?
Let's see your hands.
Get your hands
out of your jumper!
Other one. Now!
What's that?
-What is that?
-Crack cocaine, you cunt.
-Half-price heroin!
-Right, that's enough.
No, I don't even know
what it is.
-You're being detained under...
-Fuck off!
-Cunt! Cunt! Cunt!
-Quiet!
[door opens]
-[sighs]
-John, what have you done?
I'm selling drugs today.
Fuck off!
What he just said there.
That gave us grounds
to arrest him.
So what has he actually done?
[policeman]
He was carrying a package
which he claimed
was crack cocaine.
-And was it crack cocaine?
-No.
It was a bag of sugar.
But next time, they'll trust you
with the real thing.
You can't arrest him for
what might happen the next time.
Look,
he should not be locked up.
He cannae help what he says.
He has Tourette's syndrome.
He has an attitude problem,
is what he has.
Dottie's got drugs in her pussy.
Right, is he free to go?
-Yeah.
-OK. Davidson, come on.
Let's get you home where
I can keep an eye on you.
Ha-ha! Sorry.
[Dottie whispers]
I could kill you sometimes.
There you go, Dot.
Nice cup of tea.
"Dottie's got drugs
in her pussy."
Aye, sorry about that.
I'm sorry.
That estate was a bad idea.
Aye.
-What are you reading?
-A book on Tourette's.
I think you should read it.
You know, in fact,
we should both read whatever
we can get our hands on.
Learn as much as we can.
What do you think?
Aye. Aye.
-Good idea.
-Hmm.
I'm being sacked today.
[clears throat]
[man] Come in.
-All right, pal?
-Aye, John. Yeah. Sit down.
It's like a fucking sauna
in here, you cunt.
-You want me to open a window?
-No, no, no. It was just a tic.
I don't think you're a cunt
or anything.
[laughs, clears throat] John,
you'll be more than aware that
we've been looking
for a full-time...
-Sorry.
-Ah, no problem.
A full-time caretaker, yeah.
Have you found someone?
-[clears throat]
-No one's as good as me.
That was a tic.
-No, it wasn't a tic, John.
-Aye, it was. It was a tic.
It was a premonition.
John, there isn't anyone
as good as you, that is a fact.
And that's why
we would like to offer you
the position of caretaker,
permanently.
Think about it. You realise
that if you were to accept,
which we dearly hope you will,
the position comes
with accommodation.
It's not exactly a palace,
but it's comfortable.
-All right, well, um...
-Congratulations.
Aye. Thank you. Thank you.
I won't let you down.
You definitely won't, no.
You've earned it.
Right, well, uh...
I'd better be getting on.
Got some chairs to set up
and things to do.
Lovely. Thank you, John.
-Listen to that.
-Hmm.
-Silence.
-[tics]
-Oop, well... [laughs]
-Sorry. [chuckles]
[Dottie] Oh, it's a lovely
wee house, John.
-Hmm?
-Hmm.
-Tommy loved it here.
-Aye, he did.
It's just what you need.
Maybe I could get a wee dog
like Rosie.
[Dottie] Hey, and look at that.
That crow there, that is Tommy.
-[John] Don't be stupid.
-That, my friend, is a sign.
-What? No, it's true.
-[John] It's not a sign.
[Dottie] Like a spirit animal,
you know what I mean?
[crow caws]
-How you doing, Tommy?
-[John] All right, Tom?
-[they laugh]
-[Dottie] See? He's not moving.
-[knocking at door]
-Fuck off! Hello?
-Are you John?
-[John] Aye. Sorry about that.
We got your details
from the hospital.
They said you might
be able to help.
Doctors and specialists,
they talk about Tourette's,
but they haven't experienced it.
[John] Hmm.
She's never met
anyone else who has it.
[knocks on window]
Lucy, could you step outside
the car, please?
[Lucy] Fuck off!
We've got John with us.
OK, open up.
[tics] Just fuck off, you paedo.
I'm a minor.
What are you doing that for?
Stop me giving you
a smack in the face.
[chuckles]
-I'm not talking to you.
-Ah, no worries.
To be honest, it's nice to
have a few minutes off work.
Part-time slag!
-I spunked on a jellyfish today.
-You're a wanker.
-Roddy's got a little cock.
-Fuck off.
-I've got a big fucking rabbit.
-I shagged your mum.
-Fuck you. Cunt.
-[tics]
-Your dad wasted sperm.
-Your dad's a cunt.
-My dad's a paedophile.
-I'm a paedo.
[Lucy] I'm the leader
of the paedos.
[John] I raped a girl.
[Lucy]
You're on the offenders list.
-[John] I'm a fucker.
-My dad shagged your dad.
My dad's a fucking jellyfish.
-[Lucy] My mum's a virgin.
-Shall I go in?
-Maybe not.
-[John] You're a flabby cunt.
-My mum's a priest.
-You're a priest, you cunt.
You're a wank stain.
[clears throat]
-You all right, pal?
-Aye.
[both laugh]
[lighter clicks]
-What's her name?
-[John] Tilly.
Or we call her Tilly-Lilly.
-Do you like dogs?
-Yeah.
I want one, but dad says
they're too much hassle.
[John] They are, trust me.
But she helps me understand
what's going on with me,
-I think.
-Yeah.
Hello.
Ah, fuck off!
Are you OK?
Yeah, I think I just had to
get it out in the car earlier.
-Like, when it all builds up.
-Yeah.
You're pretty good at
suppressing your tics then?
Sometimes it just, like,
depends on how the day's going,
you know?
The hospital send people to me
every now and again.
But, to be honest, I'm not
really sure how much I help 'em.
I thought you were a specialist,
the way my dad was going on.
No, no. I'm not a specialist,
but I've read a bit.
Yeah.
You're the first person
I've met with Tourette's.
Does it help?
-Not at all, you wanker.
-[chuckles]
Um, no, yeah, I'd say so.
Like, you understand it
better than...
Good.
[whispers to the dog]
Did you get bullied or anything?
Oh, aye, yeah, when
I was at school, yeah, but...
now it's more about
being laughed at, or teased,
or people taking photos of you,
and whatever.
Yeah.
Some mornings, I wake up
and I can be feeling great,
and then I'll just
burst out crying.
Really?
I just wonder what I did
to deserve to be like this.
Then when I try
and get close to someone...
I think, who's gonna want to
spend their life with someone
who's gonna swear
and spit in their face?
Yeah, that's what I worry about.
Cos that'll hurt, you know.
See, sometimes, like,
if my mum's making the dinner
or something like that, and...
like, she's got the stove on,
and it's scalding hot, like...
Like, I need to put my hand
on it. Yeah, yeah.
Not even...
Like, proper smack it.
That's compulsion.
I do that as well.
-Really?
-Yeah. I can lend you a book.
Yeah. I don't know, like, I...
I don't know if you get it,
you have to do it,
you cannot walk away from it.
I know exactly what you mean.
I have to kiss the lamppost.
[laughs]
-I don't do that.
-[chuckles]
I shag letter boxes.
-Don't do that either.
-[chuckles]
Right, well, I better be
getting back to work.
-Has this helped or not?
-Yeah, no, massively.
Like, you understand it
more than...
like, the specialists do.
Good. Well, I'm on Facebook
if you want a chat.
Yeah. You're good at this.
Wait till your dad sees my bill.
I like that blue bite piece
around your neck.
Oh, it's like a...
Like, you bite it whenever
you think you're gonna tic.
I've got one.
-Yeah? This is better, though.
-[laughs]
Go on, then.
Go see Tommy. Go on, then.
Go see him.
All right, Trotter?
What can I tell you?
[clears throat]
Up the community centre today,
guess what happened.
That lead flashing on the toilet
block started leaking, again.
I've told them they can come
back down and fix it for free.
We're not paying.
Met a couple the other day.
They brought their daughter
to see me.
Twenty-four, young lady.
She's got tics.
And I was the first person she'd
ever met who has Tourette's.
Can you believe that?
You always said I should do more
to help people like me,
-kids and stuff.
-[pours water]
And I'm having a think, Trotter.
I'm having a think.
Come on then, Tilly.
Come on then, girl.
In there. Come on, guys.
[tics]
Good to see you, Lucy.
You OK?
-It's nice to see you.
-Nice to see you, too.
Bring it over here.
-Alison. Is it John?
-Alison. Yeah.
He's been screaming
since Birmingham.
-[boy] Fuck off, you wanker!
-Let's get him in and settled.
[tics] Ignore me.
-Pop!
-[various tic noises]
I just wanted to
welcome you all here.
[man] Are you my real dad?
This is the first Tourette's
weekend we're doing, so...
some of you are meeting people
with Tourette's for
the first time, and that's OK.
-Fuck off!
-Hello, pal, you OK?
-[child] Fuck off.
-[Dottie] John.
Can I ask what made you think
this was a good idea? [laughs]
-[laughter]
-[various tic noises]
-I just wanted to say...
-[child] Can I touch your penis?
Today...
Today, you are the majority,
and you're not the minority.
[cheering and applause]
So, my name's Greg,
and, just like you guys,
I have Tourette's.
I just wanna show you
a couple of things
that I do, on the drums,
to help give you
a couple of tips and tricks
to reduce your tics.
This is billed as a weekend
for those
living with Tourette's,
but that's you
as well as your kids.
Look, you're not superhuman.
This stuff is really difficult
to live with, and...
it most likely split up my own
family, my mum and dad.
So... you need to look after
each other.
Could you split yourselves
off into groups? [tics]
And I'm gonna give each group
a camera...
Put your finger on
the drumstick, about a third...
Get the fuck out
of the classroom!
I'll fucking punch your cunt in.
[man] We can all start getting
creative and tap into that side.
Homosexual man in the house.
[barks]
How do you manage
with relationships?
Personally?
For me, that has been
quite a challenge, but...
you know, as parents,
you're going to want
your kids to find a partner
and settle down,
that's only natural.
But it all goes back
to education.
The problem is not Tourette's,
the problem is that people don't
know enough about Tourette's.
The sooner
these kids are accepted,
the sooner they're understood,
the sooner they can go on and
lead a completely normal life.
-Get down!
-Empty your pockets!
Well done, Davidson.
Aye, well done, Dottie.
-Oh! Jesus Christ, you see that?
-[laughs]
Go on then! Stay.
-Come on, Tilly.
-[siren sounds]
-Stop where you are.
Put your hands on your head.
Haven't done anything wrong,
pal.
Stop where you are, Davidson.
Fuck's sakes. What is it?
[policeman]
Do you not remember me?
No.
You've done nothing wrong.
It's MacCullen.
Aye, MacCullen.
-How are you?
-I'm good.
You bald wanker.
Fuck's sakes. Sorry.
I first met John when I was
a young PC in Galashiels.
He was a young man,
it was the early '90s,
and, uh, very few people
knew what Tourette's was.
Now, the police force did not
serve him well at that time.
I didn't serve him well.
Which was why,
when I was promoted,
one of the first things I did
was find John
and ask him if he would
speak to you today. John.
OK. Thanks for having me
here today.
Um, obviously, this is a very
nerve-racking event for me.
-Fuck the police!
-[laughter]
John.
Sometimes what I say is funny,
and I even laugh myself,
but that's very different
to actively teasing,
or mocking,
or encouraging people to swear.
Everyone who lives
with Tourette's is different.
We've got our own symptoms
and tics and behaviours.
A tic can be anything. It can
be a vocal tic or a motor...
[tics] A vocal tic like that.
Or we can have eye blinking,
or people roll their eyes
sometimes, like that.
One of the things we don't
talk about with Tourette's
is the anxiety, or the
obsessive compulsive disorder,
the exhaustion from trying
to pretend nothing is wrong,
from trying
to suppress the tics.
Now, imagine trying to
hold in a thousand big sneezes.
You can do it for a while,
but then what happens?
-You'll explode.
-You explode. Good answer.
How do you manage, for example,
if you've got to go
to a library?
That's a nightmare for me.
I can't go to a library.
I'd love to,
um, but it's too quiet.
Don't engage in a conversation
with the tics, just ignore them.
The person insulting you
is guilty of nothing.
They need support
and understanding.
Thanks for listening
to me today.
I hope you've learnt something
about Tourette's.
And, yeah, thank you.
[cheering]
Cheers.
That was good.
Post! Fucking post time.
[clears throat]
[phone rings]
Ah.
-Morning, Davidson.
-Dottie. Dottie.
What's wrong?
Mr John Davidson,
for services to those
with Tourette's syndrome.
[Queen] And congratulations.
Thank you, ma'am. Thank you.
[clears throat]
-I didn't know you'd made it.
-I'm so proud, John. Oh...
Oh, we hit traffic,
and then the security...
But I was there. I saw you.
Hm. Good, good.
Meet Dottie and Chris.
This is my sister, Caroline.
I'm so glad you could come,
love.
-Nice to meet you.
-How's Mum?
-Oh, she is... she's good.
-And she's pleased.
-Good.
-You should go see her.
-Aye, I will. I will.
-[chuckles] So nice to see you.
-Really good to see you.
-Here we are, John.
-Hmm.
-Now, do you still take sugar?
-Oh, aye.
Well, that's good,
cos I've already put one in it.
[John chuckles]
Come on, now. Let's see it.
Right, OK.
[makes fanfare sound]
-There it is.
-Oh.
-Oh. It's lovely, John.
-Hmm.
-You'll have to polish it.
I'm going to get some proper
silver polish, a clean cloth,
sort of lint thing.
Get in all those bits there.
[mother] Well...
Be careful you don't lose it.
I won't.
So, you had a nice day,
with the Queen?
Oh, aye, yeah. After I told her
to go fuck herself.
-Oh, John, you didn't?
-I know. It was fine, though.
I only had three tickets, Mum,
and...
-as Caroline lives closest...
-I understand, John.
[John] No, no, it wasn't that.
It's just, you know,
the way it worked out.
[mother] Hmm.
I read about it all
in the paper, John.
Apparently you said
you didn't want
anyone to go through
what you went through.
Face the fireplace.
Fuck's sakes.
I'm sorry I wasn't good enough.
I tried my best, I did.
-[John] I know. I know, Mum.
-[sighs]
[clears throat]
I wouldn't have known
what to do, if I was you or Dad.
I couldn't have coped.
I know.
[chuckles softly]
So, there was light
at the end of the tunnel
after all, John Davidson?
Yeah.
Yep. If only we knew it...
way back then.
-Come on, you.
-[clears throat]
It's OK, John.
It's OK.
I'm sorry, John.
[John] You don't have to be.
[woman] Dear Mr Davidson,
I would like to invite you
to Nottingham University
at a time and date
that is convenient to you.
I've got a bomb!
[tuts] Sorry. Ignore me.
We share your ambition
to help people
who live with Tourette's.
In brief, we would be grateful
if you would take part
in a scientific study
to determine the effects
of median nerve stimulation
on those living with your condition.
Hey!
While it is not a cure,
initial findings suggest
it may help those with Tourette's
manage their condition.
-Here to see...
-Yours sincerely...
-Barbara Morera.
Sexy bum! Fuck's sakes.
-John?
-Are you Barbara?
-I'm Barbara.
-Nice to meet you.
-I'm John.
-[tics]
-Come this way.
-Nothing to worry about, John.
-[tics]
-This is a neuromodulation band.
-Oh, right.
We're good.
OK, just let me
set up the device
to deliver
the right parameters for you.
Good. Right, well,
you can take it for a spin.
Right.
How long will it take to work?
Let's see. Go for a walk
round the campus,
see if you notice a difference.
I'll meet you back at reception.
-OK.
-I just go around here?
Over there.
-How you doing? You all right?
-I'm good, thank you.
[sighs]
John. Have a seat.
So, how was it?
[sighs]
I'm gonna need some feedback.
Um...
I've not felt like this
since I was 14.
I feel...
calm, alert, relaxed.
I've no anxiety, no tics.
Have you ticced at all?
Once, in the corridor,
but much less aggressively.
Well, we've been working
with a group of 135 people.
About 59% are responding
in a similar way to you.
Christ.
[sighs]
I'm sorry, I just, uh...
I really don't know what to say.
-Can I keep it?
-Not yet, sorry.
But, good news is, you can
take it home for a few days.
We need you to make some notes.
How you feel,
how you sleep, any tics.
[sighs]
I stopped asking if there was
a cure, you know...
30... 30 years ago,
because the answer
was always the same.
-It's... it's not a cure.
-[exhales]
But it will give some relief
when you wear it.
[John sniffles]
[indistinct train announcements]
[sighs]
[exhales]
-Excuse me.
-Yeah?
-Sorry to interrupt.
-That's all right.
Is this the train for Sheffield?
-I hope so.
-[they laugh]
-Where are you heading?
-Edinburgh.
Then Galashiels,
so it's a long journey.
I love Edinburgh.
I have a friend who lives there.
Aye, it's well worth a visit.
[chuckles]
[sighs] It's so quiet on here.
There was a guy snoring earlier
and it was not quiet.
-Really? No. [chuckles]
-Yeah.
I was gonna go and hold
his nose. It was so loud.
Just put my headphones in.
I was like, "Oh..."
What are you listening to?
-Don't judge me.
-No, no.
-Promise?
-I won't.
-Better not.
-Cheesy pop. Here we go.
-Right, don't judge me.
-I won't.
-Know it? You don't know it?
-No.
Right, now I'm embarrassed.
Give me it back.
-I'm embarrassed.
-Don't be embarrassed.
No, I am. I feel silly now.
-Who do you like?
-Loads of people.
I'll listen to Pavarotti
in the car. I will.
[♪ "Stop Crying Your Heart Out"
by Oasis]
♪ Don't be scared
♪ You'll never change
what's been and gone
♪ May your smile
♪ Shine on
-♪ Don't be scared
-Wait here.
Wait here. Wait. Come.
Go on, then. Tilly, no.
Stay.
Wait.
Go on, then. Tilly, no.
When I feel I'm going to say it,
I try and stop myself,
but I just feel as if
I have to say it.
It's like somebody's
forcing it out of me.
Fuck off!
[tics] Oh, God. [sighs]
I never used to want to go
to school. I just...
because of getting teased.
Cunt. Fuck.
[tics]
Just keep thinking
why it has to be me and not...
folks that are criminals
or deserve it.
[tics]
John's first exclamation was,
"Ha-ha! You're gonna die."
[tics]
Fuck off.
Shut it.
Other people within the group
have got partners.
And I've just found it
so hard to find somebody
that I feel that I can trust.
Oh, Dottie.
-Smack!
-Are you all right?
You just get on with it.
You just need to kinda...
if you like,
pick up the pieces.
Filthy fags!
And I'm now in a position
to teach the teachers.
For so long,
I didn't know who I was.
I didn't know what
my purpose in life was.
I finally kinda clicked.
This is what I want to do.
I want to go and help people.
♪ Cos all of the stars
♪ Are fading away
♪ Just try not to worry
♪ You'll see them someday
♪ Just take what you need
♪ And be on your way
♪ And stop crying
your heart out
♪ We're all of us stars
♪ We're fading away
♪ Just try not to worry
♪ You'll see us someday
♪ Just take what you need
♪ And be on your way
♪ And stop crying
your heart out
♪ Stop crying your heart out